Guide to the Homer S. Brown Papers, 1918-1977 AIS.1978.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Homer S. Brown Papers
1918-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Brown, Homer S.
AIS.1978.08
6.25 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
Homer S. Brown became a member of the Allegheny County Bar Association in 1923. He was elected to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives in 1934 and became the first African-American appointed to the Pittsburgh Board of Education (1943), and elected (1949) as Allegheny County Judge. He served as Judge of the Court of Common Pleas in Allegheny County from 1956 to 1975. The Papers of Homer S. Brown consist of biographical material, correspondence from his political and judicial career, photographs, and articles and speeches written by Brown.
Biography
Homer Sylvester Brown, born in Huntington, WV, on September 23, 1896, was educated at Virginia Union University in Richmond, VA, and received his law degree from the University of Pittsburgh in 1923. In his lifetime Judge Brown also received honorary Doctor of Law degrees from Lincoln University, Virginia Union University, University of Pittsburgh, and Virginia State College.
Brown became a member of the Allegheny County Bar Association on October 26, 1923, and in 1934 he was elected to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives. During Brown's tenure in the House (1935-1950) he authored the State Fair Employment Practices Act. In 1943 he was voted the most able member of the House by the Capital News Correspondents' Association.
In 1943 Brown was the first African-American appointed to the Pittsburgh Board of Education, and in 1949 he became the first African-American to hold the position of Allegheny County Judge. In 1956 he was elected to the Court of Common Pleas and remained until 1975 when poor health forced his retirement. On the bench Brown was best known for his 1968 decision that the City of Pittsburgh's tax on hospitals, known as the "sick tax", was unconstitutional, a decision upheld by higher courts. Another historic decision came in 1973 when he ruled that prayers could be offered at graduation ceremonies. This decision was upheld by the United State Supreme Court.
Brown also served many private organizations, most notably as first President of the Pittsburgh Branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored Persons; the Centre Avenue (Pittsburgh) YMCA, where he chaired the Board of Directors; and the Board of Trustees of Virginia Union University. He also served on the White House Commission on Education (1955) and the Governor's [PA] Committee on Education (1960). Judge Brown died at his home in Pittsburgh on May 22, 1977.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers of Homer S. Brown contain materials documenting his legal and political career. Types of materials include correspondence, photographs, articles written by Brown, biographies and interview transcriptions, newspaper clippings about Brown's achievements,; newspaper clippings about his wife, Wilhelmina Byrd Brown, and her achievements; and twenty-three bound volumes of photocopies of his papers held by Virginia Union University.
The papers of Homer S. Brown are divided into nine series, more information about the individual series is available below in the contents list.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift to the Archives Service Center from Wilhelmina Byrd Brown in 1978 and 1980.
Previous Citation
Homer S. Brown Papers, 1918-1977, AIS.1978.08, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Originals
Series I of the Papers of Homer S. Brown contains a copy of the transcription of an interview conducted as part of the Pittsburgh Renaissance Oral History Project. A recording of this interview can be found in AIS.1973.24. Series IX of the Papers of Homer S. Brown are photocopies of original papers that are on deposit at Virginia Union University in Richmond, Va.
African American lawyers -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; African American legislators -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; African American judges -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Politics; Social action; Personal papers; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Pennsylvania; Legislators; African Americans -- Employment -- Law and legislation -- Pennsylvania; Brown, Wilhelmina Byrd; Brown, Homer S.; Marshall, Thurgood -- Correspondence; Pennsylvania. Court of Common Pleas (Allegheny County); Pennsylvania. General Assembly. House of Representatives; Virginia Union University (Richmond, Va.); White House Conference on Education (1955: Washington, D.C.); National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Pittsburgh Branch
- Biographical Materials, c1930-1976; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains five brief biographies about Homer S. Brown as well as a transcript of an interview with Brown conducted by Lawrence Howard and David Kurtzman for the Pittsburgh Renaissance Oral History Project on October 25, 1972.
  - Biographical Sketches and Career Highlights, c1930-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Interview of Judge Homer S. Brown by Lawrence Howard and David Kurtzman for the Pittsburgh Renaissance Project, October 25, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- Correspondence, II.
  Correspondence consists mostly of letters of congratulations for various elections and appointments as well as letters of support for Brown and his legislative decisions. Early correspondence (1919) deals with the founding of the American Legion and the role of the Black veteran in that organization. Some correspondence written during Brown's tenure as legislator (1935-1950) also concerns civil rights legislation.
  - Incoming, 1918-1976 (not all inclusive dates are represented)
    - Subject: Black Veteran's of the First World War, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Re: Predominately congragulatory letters on election to the General Assembly, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing, 1919-1963 (not all inclusive dates are represented) (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
- Personal Memorabilia, III.
  Personal memorabilia includes articles and speeches written by Brown, newspaper clippings about Brown's career, newspaper clippings about Pennsylvania politics and civil rights, and certificates and awards presented to Brown. This series contains material related to the Barr-Brown Senatorial Scholarship Committee and the Governor's Committee on Education.
  - Magazine articles by Homer S. Brown (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Education, The Architect of Tomorrow," Pennsylvania School Journal, February, 1956; 1.
    - "Financing Public Education," The Pittsburgh Teachers Bulletin, September, 1944; 2.
    - "Lynch Talk In Pennsylvania Court," American League Against War and Fascism, Pittsburgh Committee, Bulletin, September, 1936; 3.
  - Speeches by Homer S. Brown (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "The Negro in Allegheny County in 1942", 1.
    - "The Negro and the Changing Functions of Our Government," (incomplete), undated; 2.
    - "The Negro and His Struggle for Democracy", c1941-1945; 3.
    - Samuel Watson Case, 1936; 4.
    - "The Hon. Homer S. Brown Before the General Assembly of Pennsylvania," on Freedom and 'I am An American Day,', May, 19, 1941; 5.
    - "Mr. Chairman, Distinguished Platform Guests, Landies and Gentlemen," (educational program in Mississippi), undated; 6.
    - "Presentation of Flag to the Honorable Homer S. Brown, Judge of the Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, Pennsylvania", 1963; 7.
    - KDKA Radio address on the Centre Avenue Branch of the YMCA, December 20, 1936; 8.
    - Remarks prior to First Lady Eleanor Roosevelts visit to Pittsburgh to address the "Youth in Democracy" Rally at the Syria Mosque on September 4th, 1941, September 1, 1941; 9.
    - "UNESCO -- Its Fight Against Ignorance," Before the Foreign Policy Association, in the Stephen Foster Memorial Hall, March 25, 1952; 10.
    - "Education, The Architect of Tomorrow," Address by Homer S. Brown, Before the 1955 State Convention at Harrisburg of the Pennsylvania State Education Association, December 28, 1955; 11.
    - "Celebration of Bill of Rights Day in Criminal Court" In the Courts of Oyer and Terminer, General Jail Delivery and Quarter Sessions of the Peace of Allegheny County, Pennsylvania", December 12, 1957; 12.
    - "Citizenship and the [African American] Youth," for Negro Youth Day, WCAE Radio, 6 pm., January 4, 1934; 13.
    - Pittsburgh Branch NAACP at the 24th Annual National Association for the Advencement of Colored People Conference, Chicago, June 29, 1933; 14.
    - Urban Leauge of Pittsburgh, "Comparison of Camping Facilities available to Negro and White Population in Allegheny County and Evaluation of Need among Negroes", c1937; 15.
    - "Report on the First Foreign Policy Discussion Group," Foreign Policy Association and Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh," Wylie Avenue Branch, Homer S. Brown (Chairmen), prepared by Frank E. Bolden, February 13-April 9, 1952; 16.
    - "A Preface to a Postwar Balance Sheet: Toward Full Employment", c1945; 17.
    - News Release, Lincoln University, "Loss of War Would Doom Negro to Race Hatred and Persecution Worse Than Slavery, President Wright of Lincoln University Says in Baccalaureate", May 11, 1942; 18.
    - News Release, Lincoln University, "Fuller Share of the Negro In American Life Would Strengthen Nation...", May 13, 1942; 19.
    - A speech before the Pennsylvania General Assembly re: the philosophical role of government in the United States, June 30, 1941; 20.
    - A speech concerning Blacks in the medical professions, housing, government assistance in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, probably given at an Urban League event, c. 1942; 21.
    - A speech at Virginia Union University (formerly Richmond Theological Institute and Wayland Seminary) regarding the founders, undated; 22.
    - Remarks probably for a naturalization ceremony, undated; 23.
    - Excerpt on mixed races, "from Brown America: The Story of a New Race by Edwin R. Embree", 1931; 24.
    - An untitled speech, undated; 25.
  - Notes for speeches and articles (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Outline, "Kaufmann & Baer Advertising", Fall 1924; 1.
    - Outline, "Frederick Douglas," Francis Harper League, February, 19, 1930; 2.
    - Outline, untitled, subject: Christ and the NAACP, December, 1932; 3.
    - Outline, "Perseverance," Boys Conference, April 22, 1933; 4.
    - Various Outlines, subject: Abraham Lincoln, YMCA, February 11, 1934; 5.
    - Outline, "Negro Youth Looks Ahead," Conference for Negro Youth, Toledo, Ohio, April 29, 1934; 6.
    - Outline, "The Significance of Emancipation", c1936; 7.
    - Outline, 50th Anniversary, Kay Community Club, February 6, 1936; 8.
    - Outline, "Booker T. Washington," Tuskegee Program, YMCA, April 5, 1936; 9.
    - Outline, "The Place of Negro Lawyers in the County," Law Club, Janurary, 18, 1937; 10.
    - Outline, "Father & Son Banquet," Christian Street Branch of YMCA, Philadelphia, Pa., February 24, 1937; 11.
    - Outline, "James Weldon Johnson," YMCA, Youngstown, Ohio, March 19, 1938; 12.
    - Outline, subject: issues for Black populations, Second Baptist Church, Columbus, Ohio, June 26, 1938; 13.
    - Outline, "Race Relations Sunday," Coordinating Committee, Central Baptist Church, (Pittsburgh, Pa. ?), December 9, 1938; 14.
    - Outline, 11th Anniversary of the YMCA, First Baptist Church, Roanoke, Va., February 26, 1939; 15.
    - Outline, Older Boys Conference, Ogleby Park, WVa (incomplete), Octouber 18, 1940; 16.
    - Outline, subject: Employment, Education, Health, Housing, and Voting of Black Citizens, undated; 18.
    - Outline, "Security: What it means in the Post World War", c1946; 17.
    - Text, subject: Centre Avenue Branch YMCA, Pittsburgh, Pa., undated; 19.
    - Outline, "Facts for American's to Consider", undated; 20.
    - Text, subject: Freedom, undated; 21.
    - Text, "Nature of 1790", undated; 22.
    - Text, "Negro Youth in a New Social Order", undated; 23.
    - Text, "Today", undated; 24.
    - Text, Poem: The Son of God..., undated; 25.
    - Outline, "Problems that need to be solved in the Area of Race Relationship in Pennsylvania", undated; 26.
    - Outline, "Race Pride", undated; 27.
    - Outline, "Securities Commission -- Industrial Board", undated; 28.
    - Text, "Socrates", undated; 29.
    - Outline, "What of the Government of Tomorrow", undated; 30.
    - Outline, "The World Today", undated; 31.
    - Note fragments -- various unidentified speeches, undated; 32.
  - Articles about Homer S. Brown (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper clippings about Homer S. Brown, 1932-1941 (Box 2, Folder 25-30)
  - Newspaper clippings about Homer S. Brown, 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 31-43)
  - Newspaper clippings about Homer S. Brown, 1960-1975 (Box 4, Folder 44-48)
  - Newspaper clippings about Homer S. Brown, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Newspaper clippings about Pennsylvania politics and civil rights (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Certificates and awards (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Conference and banquet programs (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Barr-Brown Senatorial Scholarship Committee Papers (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Governor's Committee on Education, April 1960 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Certificates and awards (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Photographs, IV.
  In addition to photographs of Brown, the series contains photographs with Joseph Givens, Samuel Weiss, Paul Ford James, Georgina Brown, Vicky Corey, and Raymond Alexander at various stages in his career.
  - Homer S. Brown (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Identified individuals (Box 5, Folder 56)
- Scrapbooks, V.
  These scrapbooks illustrate Homer S. Brown's career primarily through newspaper clippings. One scrapbook is dedicated to his first term as judge (1949-1957).
  - 1934-1976 (Box 7, Volume unknown container)
  - Homer S. Brown's first term as judge, 1949-1957 (Box 7, Volume Unknown container 6011 for instance of Homer S. Brown's first term as judge)
- Documents from Homer S. Brown's Career, VI.
  This series includes documents from Brown's tenure in the Pennsylvania House of Representative during the 1935-1950 sessions. Of special note in material from the 1936 session is the investigation of Judge Benjamin Atlee, who insinuated that a mob lynching of an African-American defendant would have been acceptable. The 1937 session materials contain documents relating to the establishing of the Pennsylvania Labor Relations Board. Materials related to a number of proposed House bills between 1935 and 1950 are found in this series. Series VI also contains documents relating to Brown's careers in the Allegheny County Court and the Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County. These documents include a copy of Brown's opinion on the Appeal of the Hospital Council of Western Pennsylvania whereby he ruled the City of Pittsburgh Ordinance No. 676, the "Institution and Service Privilege Tax Ordinance," invalid against charitable organizations (1969).
  - Legislative Sessions, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 57)
  - Legislative Sessions, 1936 (Box 7, Folder 58)
  - Legislative Sessions, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Legislative Sessions, 1938, 1939 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Legislative Sessions, 1941, 1942 (Box 7, Folder 61)
  - Legislative Sessions, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 62)
  - Legislative Sessions, 1947, 1948, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Allegheny County Court, 1950-1953 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Court of Common Pleas of Allegheny County, 1968, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 65)
- Wilhelmina Brown (Mrs. Homer S. Brown), VII.
  This series consists of correspondence (1934-1977), newspaper clippings about Mrs. Brown (1942-1959), photocopies of awards, and programs from meetings Mrs. Brown attended.
  - Correspondence, 1934-1977 (not all inclusive dates are represented) (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Newspaper clippings about Wilhelmina Brown, 1942-1959 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Awards given to Wilhelmina Brown (photocopies) (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Programs (Box 6, Folder 69)
- Pamphlets on Racism, VIII.
  This Series contains various pamphlets on racism collected by Brown between 1945-1950.
  - Pamphlets on Racism, undated (Box 6, Folder 70)
- Collected Papers of Homer S. Brown, IX.
  The Collected Papers of Homer S. Brown are twenty-three volumes of photocopies of material on deposit at Virginia Union University in Richmond, VA. Material in these volumes were collected and compiled by Wilhemina Byrd Brown and Lawrence C. Howard. Generally, these volumes contain photocopies of Brown's correspondence, newspaper clippings, speeches, and court opinions. The volumes also contain copies of The Legislative Record from Brown's tenure in the Pennsylvania House of Representatives as well as contain newspaper clippings regarding his son Byrd Brown, a noted Pittsburgh attorney. These volumes include information on the formation of the American Legion, the investigation of Judge Benjamin Atlee, lynchings in the southern states of America, and African American rights in education, hospitals and state unions. Of particular interest are materials related to Brown's fight against Governor Earle's bill to change the Pennsylvania Grand Jury System in 1938 (Vol. 4); the "Report of Legislative Committee Appointed Pursuant to Resolution No. 27, Serial 53 of the House of Representatives of the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, " 1939, regarding charges of discrimination against the City of Pittsburgh in hiring of African-Americans as teachers (Vol. 5); and a number of judicial opinions written by Judge Homer S. Brown between 1961-1974 (vols. 20-23).
  - 1919-1943, 1972 (Box 8, Volume 1-8)
  - 1946 (Box 9, Volume 9)
  - 1941-1942 (Box 9, Volume 10)
  - 1947-1949 (Box 9, Volume 11)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 9, Volume 12-13)
  - 1936-1938, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Volume 14)
  - 1938-1941, 1943, 1957, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Volume 15)
  - 1963-1969 (Box 9, Volume 16)
  - 1967-1973 (Box 10, Volume 17)
  - 1936-1941, 1951-1953, 1959-1969 (Box 10, Volume 18)
  - 1941-1949, 1977 (Box 10, Volume 19)
  - 1961-1974 (Box 10, Volume 20)
  - 1969-1974 (Box 10, Volume 21-22)
  - 1965-1970 (Box 10, Volume 23)